http://www.mitre.org/publications/systems-engineering-guide/enterprise-engineering/engineering-informationintensive-enterprises/privacy-systems-engineering

MITRE
AboutCorporate OverviewOur HistoryMission and ValuesVisiting MITRELeadershipExecutive TeamBoard of TrusteesFellowsTechnical FellowsVisiting FellowsAwards and RecognitionCorporate Social ResponsibilityBuilding a Foundation for the FutureMITRE Staff Cultivates Los Angeles' Science EcosystemBringing Real World STEM to StudentsBuilding Partnerships and Diversity, One Engineering Conference at a TimeHow a Can of Soda Changed a Cafeteria DesignHow to Grow Computer Scientists? Start with KindergartnersMITRE Participates in Outside the Box DayA Conference Dedicated to Women's LeadershipNurturing Under-Represented Engineering StudentsYoung Women and EngineeringConnecting with Our Sponsor CommunitiesStudent Cadets Learn What It Takes to "Play at Work All Day"A Fishing Experience for Disabled VetsThe Undersea World of Frank LewisPromoting a Culture of Health and WellnessA Clothing Drive That Never EndedEnriching the Communities Where We LiveFighting Polio in Africa, Thanks to MITRE's Civic Leave ProgramBuilding a Better World, One Home at a TimeOur Green BuildingsRolling Up Their SleevesCulture of Knowledge SharingLocations and DirectionsContact UsGeneral InquiriesCentersWe Operate FFRDCsSpecial Access for Cities and StatesNational Security Engineering CenterWho We AreHistory and AwardsWhere We FocusDelivering Mission-Critical CapabilitiesSolving Global Information ChallengesIntegrating Solutions Across GovernmentCreating Transformational TechnologiesWho We HireWhat's NewCenter for Advanced Aviation System DevelopmentWho We AreHistoryAwardsWhere We FocusTransforming the National Airspace System (NextGen)Improving National Airspace System PerformanceAviation SafetyGlobal AviationAviation Research and DevelopmentTransforming TransportationParticipate in Aviation ResearchWho We HireWhat's NewCenter for Enterprise ModernizationWho We AreWhere We FocusTax, Revenue & Financial System TransformationFraud, Compliance & Financial IntegrityEconomic Infrastructure Modernization & ProtectionVeterans Health & Benefits ModernizationWho We HireWhat's NewHomeland Security Systems Engineering and Development InstituteWho We AreThe HSSEDI DifferenceEngage With UsWhere We FocusPrevent TerrorismSecure and Manage BordersEnforce and Administer Immigration LawsSafeguard and Secure CyberspaceStrengthen National Preparedness and ResilienceMature and Strengthen Homeland SecurityWho We HireWhat's NewJudiciary Engineering and Modernization CenterWho We AreWhere We FocusWhat's NewCMS Alliance to Modernize HealthcareWho We AreWhere We FocusWho We HireWhat's NewNational Cybersecurity FFRDCWho We AreWhere We FocusCapabilitiesOverviewMITRE LabsTechnical FellowsSystems EngineeringMITRE’s Systems Engineering RoleFellowship FAQsOverviewSE ResourcesCollaborationsMITRE Systems Engineering Fellowship Program for Federal EmployeesFellowship ExperienceEligibility and ApplicationFellowship FAQsSystem of Systems Engineering Collaborators Information ExchangeCybersecurityOverviewCyber Connections and DirectionsThinking ForwardThinking Forward: Cyber DefenseThinking Forward: CyberPhysicalHuman WorldCybersecurity ResourcesAwareness & TrainingStandardsToolsWhat's NewCyber Threat IntelligenceSituation AwarenessResiliencySecuring Civil SpaceThreat-based DefensePartnershipOperational InnovationAcquisition EffectivenessOverviewAcquisition ManagementCost AnalysisContractingAcquisition InitiativesAffordability Engineering FrameworkContinuous CompetitionAgile AcquisitionChallenge Based AcquisitionThe Science of AcquisitionEnhanced Scenario Based MethodAdvanced TechnologiesOverviewInformation SystemsCloud ComputingPrivacyService-Oriented ArchitectureSocial Software & CollaborationSignal ProcessingMobile TechnologiesData Science and AnalyticsSymphony™ Automated Secure PlatformSymphony in ActionMission PacksResearchOverviewWhat's NewMission-focused ResearchAgile Connected GovernmentAviation and TransportationCyberDecision ScienceNudge LabNudge Studies in ActionNudge FAQsHealthClinical Analytics for HealthcareNational Security NextNanotechnologyResearch and DevelopmentNanosystems Student ProgramsSensing, Processing, and ExploitationTechnology FuturesTechnology TransferTechnology LicensingSocial Radar TechnologiesFastLicensePatentsOpen Source SoftwarePartnerships & CollaborationMITRE ChallengeMITRE Challenge Eligibility VerificationEligibility Verification FAQsMITRE Challenge IoTIoT LeaderboardIoT FAQsMITRE Challenge UASUAS Challenge FinalistsUAS Challenge Eligibility OverviewUAS Challenge ComponentsUAS Challenge DetailsUAS Challenge Submission DetailsUAS FAQsSurface to SpaceResearch and Related
NewsSurface to Space ArchitectureSpace Policy PodcastCenter for Technology & National SecurityCenter for Data-Driven PolicyCareersWorking at MITREValuing DiversityCollaboration and InnovationBenefitsProfessional DevelopmentWork-Life BalanceEmployee VoicesOur Hiring ProcessJob OpeningsAdvanced SearchStudent ProgramsEarly High School InternshipsSummer InternshipCampus EventsCo-ops & InternsRecent GraduatesStudent VoicesMilitary to MITREAcademic EngagementSE FellowshipPublicationsAll PublicationsProject StoriesTechnical PapersSystems Engineering GuideAbout the SEGThe Evolution of Systems EngineeringThe Essence of MITRE’s Systems EngineeringSEG Table of ContentsEnterprise EngineeringComprehensive ViewpointSystems ThinkingSystems Engineering Strategies for Uncertainty and ComplexityTools to Enable a Comprehensive ViewpointEnterprise Planning and ManagementIT GovernancePortfolio ManagementHow to Develop a Measurement CapabilityEnterprise Technology, Information, and InfrastructureIT Infrastructure EngineeringIT Service ManagementInformation and Data ManagementRadio Frequency Spectrum ManagementEngineering Information-Intensive EnterprisesArchitectures FederationDesign PatternsComposable Capabilities on Demand (CCOD)Open Source SoftwarePrivacy EngineeringPrivacy Requirements Definition and TestingSystems of SystemsEngineering Systems in the Context of Systems of SystemsTreating Systems of Systems as SystemsSystems Engineering Life-Cycle Processes as Applied to Systems of SystemsSystems Engineering for Mission AssuranceCyber Mission AssuranceCrown Jewels AnalysisCyber Threat Susceptibility AssessmentCyber Risk Remediation AnalysisSecure Code ReviewSupply Chain Risk
ManagementTransformation Planning and Organizational ChangePerforming Organizational AssessmentsFormulation of Organizational Transformation StrategiesStakeholder
Assessment and ManagementEffective Communication and InfluencePlanning for Successful User AdoptionEnterprise GovernanceCommunity of Interest and/or Community of PracticeStandards Boards and BodiesPolicy AnalysisMITRE FFRDC Independent AssessmentsPlanning and Managing Independent AssessmentsSE Life-Cycle Building BlocksConcept DevelopmentOperational Needs AssessmentConcept of OperationsOperational RequirementsHigh-Level Conceptual DefinitionRequirements EngineeringEliciting, Collecting, and Developing RequirementsAnalyzing and Defining RequirementsSpecial Considerations for Conditions of Uncertainty: Prototyping and ExperimentationSystem ArchitectureArchitectural Frameworks, Models, and ViewsApproaches to Architecture DevelopmentArchitectural PatternsSystem Design and DevelopmentDevelop System-Level Technical RequirementsDevelop Top-Level System DesignAssess the Design's Ability to Meet the System RequirementsSystems IntegrationIdentify and Assess Integration and Interoperability (I&I) ChallengesDevelop and Evaluate Integration and Interoperability (I&I) Solution StrategiesAssess Integration Testing ApproachesInterface ManagementTest and EvaluationCreate and Assess Test and Evaluation StrategiesAssess Test and Evaluation Plans and ProceduresVerification and ValidationCreate and Assess Certification and Accreditation StrategiesImplementation, O & M, and TransitionOther SE Life-Cycle Building Blocks ArticlesSpanning the Operational Space: How to Select Use Cases and Mission ThreadsAcquiring and Incorporating Post-Fielding Operational Feedback into Future DevelopmentsTest and Evaluation of Systems of SystemsVerification and Validation of Simulation ModelsAffordability, Efficiency, and EffectivenessAcquisition Systems EngineeringAcquisition Program PlanningAnalyses of AlternativesAcquisition Management MetricsAssessing Technical MaturityTechnology PlanningLife-Cycle Cost EstimationIntegrated Master Schedule (IMS)/Integrated Master Plan (IMP) ApplicationPerformance EngineeringComparison of Investment AnalysesSource Selection Preparation and EvaluationPicking the Right ContractorRFP Preparation and Source SelectionProgram Acquisition Strategy FormulationAgile Acquisition StrategyEvolutionary Acquisition"Big Bang" AcquisitionContractor EvaluationData Driven Contractor Evaluations and Milestone ReviewsEarned Value ManagementCompetitive PrototypingRisk ManagementRisk Management Approach and PlanRisk IdentificationRisk Impact Assessment and PrioritizationRisk Mitigation Planning, Implementation, and Progress MonitoringRisk Management ToolsConfiguration ManagementHow to Control a Moving BaselineConfiguration Management ToolsIntegrated Logistics SupportReliability, Availability, and MaintainabilityManaging Energy EfficiencyQuality Assurance and MeasurementEstablishing a Quality Assurance Program in the Systems Acquisition or Government Operational OrganizationHow to Conduct Process and Product Reviews Across BoundariesContinuous Process ImprovementImplementing and Improving Systems Engineering Processes for the Acquisition OrganizationMatching Systems Engineering Process Improvement Frameworks/Solutions with Customer NeedsNewsPress ReleasesCOVID-19 Insights & ImpactCEO LetterFocal PointsPromoting EquityPandemic ResponseCritical InfrastructureAerospace and TransportationAI and Machine LearningCommunity and BelongingCOVID-19Great Power CompetitionHealth OutcomesElection IntegrityExperimentation and ResearchMITRE Focal Points NewsletterIn the NewsMedia ResourcesCorporate EventsMITRE ExchangeMITRE Newsletter
About the SEG
SEG Table of Contents
Enterprise Engineering
SE Life-Cycle Building Blocks
Acquisition Systems Engineering
Privacy Engineering
Print
Definition: Privacy is generally defined as the ability of an individual to exercise control over the collection, use, and dissemination of his or her Personally Identifiable Information (PII). Privacy issues arise with the collection, use, maintenance, and disclosure of PII.
PII is defined as “information which can be used to distinguish or trace an individual’s identity, such as their name, social security number, biometric records, etc. alone, or when combined with other personal or identifying information which is linked or linkable to a specific individual, such as date and place of birth, mother’s maiden name, etc. [1]” Determining whether information is PII “demands a case-by-case assessment of the specific risk that an individual can be identified. [2]"
Keywords: E-Government Act, Fair Information Practice Principles (FIPPs), personally identifiable information (PII), privacy, Privacy Act, privacy impact assessment (PIA), system of records
MITRE SE Roles & Expectations: MITRE systems engineers (SEs) are expected to recognize when privacy is within the scope of the system being developed. They should work with the sponsoring organization to translate the agency’s privacy principles, policies, and procedures into actionable engineering requirements applicable to the focus of the system.
Background
Privacy is based on the implementation of Fair Information Practice Principles (FIPPs), which were initially developed in 1973 by a federal advisory committee, commissioned because of concern over the harmful consequences that computerized data systems could have on the privacy of personal information. Different versions of the FIPPs have been defined. One version is found in the Guidelines on the Protection of Privacy and Transborder Flows of Personal Data [3] that were developed by the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) in 1980 and later replaced by the 2013 OECD Privacy Framework [4]. The principles in the OECD documents have been widely adopted and form the basis for many privacy laws worldwide (see Table 1).
Table 1. 2013 OECD Privacy Framework Privacy Principles
Principle
Description
Collection limitation
There should be limits to the collection of personal data and any such data should be obtained by lawful and fair means and, where appropriate, with the knowledge or consent of the data subject.
Data quality
Personal data should be relevant to the purposes for which they are to be used and, to the extent necessary for those purposes, should be accurate, complete and kept up to date.
Purpose specification
The purposes for which personal data are collected should be specified no later than at the time of data collection, and the subsequent use limited to the fulfilment of those purposes or such others as are not incompatible with those purposes and as are specified on each occasion of change of purpose.
Use limitation
Personal data should not be disclosed, made available, or otherwise used for purposes other than those specified in accordance with the Purpose Specification Principle except a) with the consent of the data subject or b) by the authority of law.
Security safeguards
Personal data should be protected by reasonable security safeguards against such risks as loss or unauthorized access, destruction, use, modification, or disclosure of data.
Openness
There should be a general policy of openness about developments, practices, and policies with respect to personal data. Means should be readily available of establishing the existence and nature of personal data, and the main purposes of their use, as well as the identity and usual residence of the data controller.
Individual participation
Individuals should have the right:
a) To obtain from a data controller, or otherwise, confirmation of whether or not the data controller has data relating to them.
b) To have communicated to them, data relating to them
i. Within a reasonable time.
ii. At a charge, if any, that is not excessive.
iii. In a reasonable manner.
iv. In a form that is readily intelligible to them.
c) To be given reasons if a request made under subparagraphs (a) and (b) is denied, and to be able to challenge such denial.
d) To challenge data relating to them and, if the challenge is successful, to have the data erased, rectified, completed, or amended.
Accountability
A data controller should be accountable for complying with measures that give effect to the principles stated above.
The centerpiece of the federal government's legal framework for privacy protection, the Privacy Act of 1974 [5], is based on the FIPPs and provides safeguards for information maintained by federal agencies. Specifically, the act places limitations on agencies' collection, disclosure, and use of personal information maintained in systems of records. The act describes a "record" as any item, collection, or grouping of information about an individual that is maintained by an agency and contains his or her name or another personal identifier. It also defines "system of records" as a group of records under the control of any agency from which information is retrieved by the name of the individual or by an individual identifier. The Privacy Act requires that when agencies establish or make changes to a system of records, they must notify the public through a notice in the Federal Register [6]. Agencies are allowed to claim exemptions from some of the provisions of the Privacy Act if the records are used for certain purposes, such as law enforcement. However, no system of records can be exempted from all of the Privacy Act's provisions. For example, agencies must publish the required notice in the Federal Register for all systems of records, even those that involve classified information. This ensures that the federal government does not maintain secret systems of records—a major goal of the act.
More recently, in 2002, Congress enacted the E-Government Act [7] to, among other things, enhance protection for personal information in government information systems or information collections by requiring that agencies conduct privacy impact assessments (PIAs). A PIA is an analysis of how personal information is collected, stored, shared, and managed in a federal system; it is used to identify privacy risks and mitigating controls to address those risks. Agencies must conduct PIAs (1) before developing or procuring information technology that collects, maintains, or disseminates information that is in identifiable form, or (2) before initiating any new data collections of information in an identifiable form that will be collected, maintained, or disseminated using information technology if the same questions are asked of 10 or more people. Individual PIAs may vary significantly depending on the specifics of department/agency guidance and the scope and sensitivity of PII collected, used, and disseminated.
Privacy Is Not Synonymous with Security
Privacy focuses on the individual's ability to control the collection, use, and dissemination of their PII, whereas security provides the mechanisms to ensure confidentiality and integrity of information, and the availability of information technology systems. The concepts of privacy and security, however, do intersect. Specifically, certain IT controls established to ensure confidentiality and integrity from a security perspective also support privacy objectives. For example, access controls ensure that only authorized individuals can read, alter, or delete PII. Such controls help achieve confidentiality and integrity from a security standpoint. In addition, when a system processes or stores PII, these IT controls ensure that users can access only the specific PII needed to perform their jobs; this helps ensure that use of PII is limited to authorized purposes (purpose specification) and protected from unauthorized access, destruction, and disclosure (security safeguards). Although establishing good security practices helps protect privacy, these practices are not, in and of themselves, sufficient to fully address the FIPPs.
Many organizations rely on the following activities to address privacy risks:
Policy
Risk assessments (e.g., PIAs)
Notice
Records management
Accounting of disclosures
Data flow mapping
Data loss prevention
Metrics
Yet privacy risks remain and privacy breaches continue to rise. Why? Because these things alone do not proactively address privacy risks at the appropriate level of specificity for a given system. To be effective, systems containing PII must be capable of preventing or minimizing the effect of human error or fallibility and appropriately constraining system actions.
To adequately address privacy risks, systems that manage PII must behave in a privacy-sensitive manner. Systems engineering processes are a largely untapped opportunity to embed privacy requirements into organizational activities in a way that provides major impact and will proactively address privacy risks. (See Figure 1.)
Figure 1. Addressing Privacy Risk in Systems Engineering ProcessesPrivacy Engineering Framework
Privacy engineering is a systematic, risk-driven process that operationalizes the Privacy by Design (PbD) philosophical framework within IT systems by:
Segmenting PbD into activities aligned with those of the systems engineering life cycle (SELC) and supported by particular methods that account for privacy’s distinctive characteristics.
Defining and implementing requirements for addressing privacy risks within the SELC using architectural, technical point, and policy controls. Privacy requirements must be defined in terms of implementable system functionality and properties. Privacy risks, including those beyond compliance risks, are identified and adequately addressed.
Supporting deployed systems by aligning system usage and enhancement with a broader privacy program.
The goal is to integrate privacy into existing systems engineering processes; it is not to create a separate new process. Figure 2 illustrates how the core privacy engineering activities map to stages of the classic systems engineering life cycle. A mapping exists for every systems engineering life cycle, including agile development, because every life cycle includes the core activities in some form.
Figure 2. Privacy Engineering FrameworkThe primary privacy engineering activities and methods are listed in Table 2.
Table 2. Privacy Engineering Activities and Methods
Life Cycle Activity
Privacy Method
Method Description
Privacy Requirements Definition: Specification of system privacy properties in a way that supports system design and development
Baseline & custom privacy system requirements
Granular technical privacy requirements derived from first principles and from risk analysis
Privacy empirical theories & abstract concepts
Methodological constructs based on theories of privacy and socio-technical systems
Privacy Design and Implementation: Representation and implementation of those elements of the system that support defined privacy requirements
Fundamental privacy design concepts
Explicit or tacit consensus understandings of how privacy works in a system
Privacy empirical theories & abstract concepts
Methodological constructs based on theories of privacy and socio-technical systems
Privacy design tools
Specific techniques for achieving privacy
Privacy heuristics
Experientially developed rules of thumb regarding privacy properties of artifacts
Privacy Verification and Validation: Confirmation that defined privacy requirements have been correctly implemented and reflect stakeholder expectations
Privacy tesing & review
Executable tests and targeted document reviews associated with privacy requirements
Operational synchronization
Analysis of privacy policies & procedures and system behaviors for inconsistencies
For additional details on privacy engineering inputs, activities, and outputs for each life-cycle activity in Table 2, see MITRE's Privacy Engineering Framework. See the SEG's Privacy Requirements Definition and Testing article for more information on addressing privacy within requirements definition and testing activities.
Best Practices and Lessons Learned
Privacy is not ensured by policy alone. Privacy by Design (PbD) advances the view that privacy cannot be assured solely by compliance with regulatory frameworks; rather, privacy assurance must become an organization’s default mode of operation. PbD applies to information technology, accountable business practices, and physical design. Adequate privacy requires thoughtful integration with every layer of an organization, including:
Organization policies and governance
Business processes
Standard operating procedures
System and network architectures
IT system design and development practices
Management of data sources
Consider the use of enterprise privacy-enhancing technologies (ePETs). ePETs are enterprise-oriented, data stewardship tools that help organizations achieve their business goals while appropriately managing PII throughout the information life cycle. These technologies may or may not be privacy-specific. ePETs include tools that can desensitize static data in databases by applying a variety of transformations, including masking and obfuscation. Desensitized data can then be used for testing and other purposes without unnecessarily disclosing individuals' PIIs. Another example is enterprise digital rights management, which can be used to impose limitations on the usage of digital content and devices, and can also be used to enforce limitations on the use of PII.
References & Resources
Office of Management and Budget (OMB), May 7, 2007, Safeguarding Against and Responding to the Breach of Personally Identifiable Information, Memorandum M-07-16.
Office of Management and Budget (OMB), June 25, 2010, Guidance for Agency Use of Third-Party Websites and Applications, Memorandum M-10-23.
Office of Economic Cooperation and Development, September 23, 1980, OECD Guidelines on the Protection of Privacy and Transborder Flows of Personal Data.
Office of Economic Cooperation and Development, 2013, The OECD Privacy Framework.
Privacy Act of 1974, as amended, 5 U.S.C. § 552a.
Federal Register, National Archives and Records Administration, accessed August 18, 2014.
e-Government Act of 2002, Public Law 107-347.
Additional References and Resources
Kendall, D., ed., 2013, U.S. Government Privacy: Essential Policies and Practices for Privacy Professionals, Portsmouth, N.H., International Association of Privacy Professionals.
Information and Privacy Commissioner, Ontario, Canada, Privacy by Design Centre of Excellence, About PbD, accessed on August 18, 2014.
The MITRE Corporation, August 2014, Privacy Engineering Framework.
All Publications
Project Stories
Technical Papers
Systems Engineering GuideAbout the SEGThe Evolution of Systems Engineering
The Essence of MITRE’s Systems Engineering
SEG Table of Contents
Enterprise EngineeringComprehensive ViewpointSystems Thinking
Systems Engineering Strategies for Uncertainty and Complexity
Tools to Enable a Comprehensive Viewpoint
Enterprise Planning and ManagementIT Governance
Portfolio Management
How to Develop a Measurement Capability
Enterprise Technology, Information, and InfrastructureIT Infrastructure Engineering
IT Service Management
Information and Data Management
Radio Frequency Spectrum Management
Engineering Information-Intensive EnterprisesArchitectures Federation
Design Patterns
Composable Capabilities on Demand (CCOD)
Open Source Software
Privacy Engineering
Privacy Requirements Definition and Testing
Systems of SystemsEngineering Systems in the Context of Systems of Systems
Treating Systems of Systems as Systems
Systems Engineering Life-Cycle Processes as Applied to Systems of Systems
Systems Engineering for Mission AssuranceCyber Mission Assurance
Crown Jewels Analysis
Cyber Threat Susceptibility Assessment
Cyber Risk Remediation Analysis
Secure Code Review
Supply Chain Risk
Management
Transformation Planning and Organizational ChangePerforming Organizational Assessments
Formulation of Organizational Transformation Strategies
Stakeholder
Assessment and Management
Effective Communication and Influence
Planning for Successful User Adoption
Enterprise GovernanceCommunity of Interest and/or Community of Practice
Standards Boards and Bodies
Policy Analysis
MITRE FFRDC Independent AssessmentsPlanning and Managing Independent Assessments
SE Life-Cycle Building BlocksConcept DevelopmentOperational Needs Assessment
Concept of Operations
Operational Requirements
High-Level Conceptual Definition
Requirements EngineeringEliciting, Collecting, and Developing Requirements
Analyzing and Defining Requirements
Special Considerations for Conditions of Uncertainty: Prototyping and Experimentation
System ArchitectureArchitectural Frameworks, Models, and Views
Approaches to Architecture Development
Architectural Patterns
System Design and DevelopmentDevelop System-Level Technical Requirements
Develop Top-Level System Design
Assess the Design's Ability to Meet the System Requirements
Systems IntegrationIdentify and Assess Integration and Interoperability (I&I) Challenges
Develop and Evaluate Integration and Interoperability (I&I) Solution Strategies
Assess Integration Testing Approaches
Interface Management
Test and EvaluationCreate and Assess Test and Evaluation Strategies
Assess Test and Evaluation Plans and Procedures
Verification and Validation
Create and Assess Certification and Accreditation Strategies
Implementation, O & M, and Transition
Other SE Life-Cycle Building Blocks ArticlesSpanning the Operational Space: How to Select Use Cases and Mission Threads
Acquiring and Incorporating Post-Fielding Operational Feedback into Future Developments
Test and Evaluation of Systems of Systems
Verification and Validation of Simulation Models
Affordability, Efficiency, and Effectiveness
Acquisition Systems EngineeringAcquisition Program PlanningAnalyses of Alternatives
Acquisition Management Metrics
Assessing Technical Maturity
Technology Planning
Life-Cycle Cost Estimation
Integrated Master Schedule (IMS)/Integrated Master Plan (IMP) Application
Performance Engineering
Comparison of Investment Analyses
Source Selection Preparation and EvaluationPicking the Right Contractor
RFP Preparation and Source Selection
Program Acquisition Strategy FormulationAgile Acquisition Strategy
Evolutionary Acquisition
"Big Bang" Acquisition
Contractor EvaluationData Driven Contractor Evaluations and Milestone Reviews
Earned Value Management
Competitive Prototyping
Risk ManagementRisk Management Approach and Plan
Risk Identification
Risk Impact Assessment and Prioritization
Risk Mitigation Planning, Implementation, and Progress Monitoring
Risk Management Tools
Configuration ManagementHow to Control a Moving Baseline
Configuration Management Tools
Integrated Logistics SupportReliability, Availability, and Maintainability
Managing Energy Efficiency
Quality Assurance and MeasurementEstablishing a Quality Assurance Program in the Systems Acquisition or Government Operational Organization
How to Conduct Process and Product Reviews Across Boundaries
Continuous Process ImprovementImplementing and Improving Systems Engineering Processes for the Acquisition Organization
Matching Systems Engineering Process Improvement Frameworks/Solutions with Customer Needs
Download the SEG
MITRE's Systems Engineering Guide
Download for EPUBDownload for Amazon KindleDownload a PDF
Questions?
Contact the SEG Team
Privacy
Terms
Contact
Remote Access
Partnership Network
MITRE is proud to be an equal opportunity employer. MITRE recruits, employs, trains, compensates, and promotes regardless of age, color, race, disability, marital status, national and ethnic origin, political affiliation, religion, sexual orientation, gender identity, veteran status, family medical or genetic information, and other protected status.
MITRE intends to maintain a website that is fully accessible to all individuals. If you are unable to search or apply for jobs and would like to request a reasonable accommodation for any part of MITRE’s employment process, please contact MITRE’s Recruiting Help Line at 703-983-8226 or email at recruitinghelp@mitre.org
Copyright © 1997-2020, The MITRE Corporation. All rights reserved.
MITRE is a registered trademark of The MITRE Corporation. Material on this site may be copied and distributed with permission only.
